Axel Künstner

Bioinformatician and next-generation sequencing data specialist

I am working as a Data Scientist and Bioinformatician in the Medical Systems Biology group at the University of Lübeck. My research encompasses the detection of unknown correlations to illuminate genetic causalities and pathomechanisms of rare diseases and in cancer by analyzing high-throughput data (e.g. whole genome/exome sequencing data, RNA-seq data, proteomics data). Additionally, I have a strong background in analysing microbiome data to correlate disease phenotypes with changes in bacterial community composition. I have published over 40 peer-reviewed papers, including 15 first or last authorships (h-index 21).

Work History

2014-09 - present

Postdoctoral Researcher

Lübeck Institute of Experimental Dermatology, University of Lübeck, Lübeck/Germany

- · Core facility for data analysis
- · Next generation sequencing data analyst
- Strong focus on microbiome, tumor and rare diseases
- · Statistical modeling and machine learning
- Molecular Tumor Board

2014-09

Postdoctoral Researcher

- 2016-09

Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Biology, Plön/Germany

- Microbiome analysis of skin and gut (human and mice)
- Consultant for project design and statistical analysis

2012-02 - 2014-08

Postdoctoral Researcher

Department of Molecular Biology, Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology, Tübingen/Germany

Guppy Genome Sequencing Project

2007-03

Scientific assistant

- 2007-07

Institute for Medical Informatics, Statistics and Epidemiology, University of Leipzig, Leipzig/Germany

ChIP-on-Chip data analysis and software development

2000-12

Social insurance clerk

- 2001-08

Gmünder Ersatzkasse, Leipzig/Germany

Customer care in scope of marketing/public relations

2000-01

Civil Service

- 2000-11

ASB Leipzig, Leipzig/Germany

Driver for handicapped people

1999-04

Social insurance clerk

- 1999-12 Gmünder Ersatzkasse, Leipzig/Germany

Customer care in scope of insurance benefit

Personal Info

Date of birth

1977-06-30

Place of birth

Leipzig

Citizenship

German

Email

axel.kunstner@gmail.com

Phone

+491775576577

Address

Hauptstr. 7e

23627 Groß Grönau

GitHub

https://github.com/kunstner

LinkedIn

www.linkedin.com/in/axel-künstnerb2a5315b

Skills

Programming R, Perl,

bash

Statistics and

Bioinformatics

Next generation sequencing data

Software

R/rstudio

GATK

Languages

German

English

Swedish

Russian

Education

2007-08 - 2011-11	Evolutionary Biology Centre, Uppsala University, Uppsala/Sweden
2005-08	PhD, Evolutionary Biology Uppsala University, Uppsala/Sweden
- 2006-12 2001-10	Master of Science, Computer Science University of Leipzig, Leipzig/Germany
- 2005-07	Pre-Diploma, Computer Sciences and Biology
1996-08 - 1999-04	Gmünder Ersatzkasse, Leipzig/Germany Social insurance clerk
1992-09 - 1996-07	GC. Lichtenberg Gymnasium, Leipzig/Germany A-Level